I'd like to take you back about seven years in my life.
約７年前の自分を 振り返ってみたいと思います
Friday afternoon,
2009年
a few days before Christmas 2009.
クリスマス数日前の 金曜日の午後
I was the director of operations
私はサンフランシスコにある
at a consumer products company in San Francisco,
消費財会社の事業部門で部長として 働いていており
and I was called into a meeting that was already in progress.
進行中の会議に 呼び出されました
That meeting turned out to be my exit interview.
その会議は 結局 退職者面接だったのですが
I was fired, along with several others.
他の何人かと共に 私は 解雇されました
I was 64 years old at the time.
当時 私は64歳でしたので
It wasn't completely unexpected.
ある程度 予測はしていました
I signed a stack of papers,
私は書類の山にサインし
gathered my personal effects,
私物をまとめて
and left to join my wife
職場を出て 妻と待合せていた
who was waiting for me at a nearby restaurant,
近くのレストランに 茫然自失の状態で
completely unaware.
向かいました
Fast-forward several hours,
数時間 早送りすると
we both got really silly drunk.
私たちは 完璧な 酔っ払いになっていました
(Laughter)
（笑）
So, 40 plus years of continuous employment
40有余年に渡って 大小様々な会社で
for a variety of companies, large and small,
働いてきた時代も
was over.
終焉を迎えました
I had a good a network, a good reputation --
私には 強力な人脈と 名声があるので
I thought I'd be just fine.
大丈夫だと思いました
I was an engineer in manufacturing and packaging.
私は製造と製品パッケージの エンジニアとしての
I had a good background.
優れた経歴がありました
Retirement was, like for so many people,
多くの人々もそうですが 私にとって 引退することは
simply not an option for me.
選択肢の中に ありませんでした
So I turned to consulting for the next couple of years
その後 ２年ほど コンサルティングなどしていましたが
without any passion whatsoever.
これといった意欲は 生まれませんでした
And then an idea began to take root,
それから 環境への関心が芽生え
born from my concern for our environment.
その考えが 徐々に 根を下ろし始めたのです
I wanted to build my own business,
私は起業しようと思いました
designing and manufacturing biodegradable packaging from waste --
紙、農業廃棄物、 繊維くずといった廃棄物から
paper, agricultural, even textile waste --
生物分解できる包装を 設計製造して
replacing the toxic, disposable plastic packaging
私たちが皆 手放せなくなっている 有害な使い捨てのプラスティック包装を
to which we've all become addicted.
置き換えるのです
This is called clean technology,
これはクリーンテクノロジーというもので
and it felt really meaningful to me.
非常にやり甲斐を感じました
A venture that could help to reduce the billions of pounds
毎年廃棄される 使い捨て プラスティック包装を
of single-use plastic packaging dumped each year
数十万トンも削減しようという 構想です
and polluting our land, our rivers and our oceans,
プラスチックの廃棄は 土壌、河川、海洋を汚染し
and left for future generations to resolve --
将来の世代に問題を 背負わせています
our grandchildren,
私たちの孫の世代に―
my grandchildren.
私の孫たちにです
And so now at the age of 66,
そこで66歳のときに改めて
with 40 years of experience,
40年間の職業経験を活かし
I became an entrepreneur for the very first time.
初めて起業しました
(Cheers)
（歓声）
(Applause)
（拍手）
Thank you.
ありがとう
But there's more.
まだあります
(Laughter)
（笑）
Lots of issues to deal with:
取り組むべき課題は山積みです
manufacturing, outsourcing, job creation,
製造、外注、雇用創出
patents, partnerships, funding --
特許、パートナーシップ、資金調達―
these are all typical issues for a start-up,
これらはすべて 新規事業に付き物の課題ですが
but hardly typical for me.
私にとっては 全く違いました
And a word about funding.
資金調達についてです
I live and work in San Francisco.
私はサンフランシスコに住み 働いています
And if you're looking for funding,
もし資金調達先を探すなら
you are typically going to compete with some very young people
通常はハイテク産業出身の とても若い人たちと
from the high-tech industry,
競争することになるのです
and it can be very discouraging and intimidating.
気力が失せますし 怖気づきます
I have shoes older than most of these people.
若者たちが生まれる前に買った靴も 持っているというのに
(Laughter)
（笑）
I do.
ほんとです
But five years later,
しかし５年後
I'm thrilled and proud to share with you
私がワクワクしながら 自信をもってお伝えするのは
that our revenues have doubled every year,
毎年 売り上げが２倍に なっていることです
we have no debt,
負債もありません
we have several marquee clients,
大口顧客も 若干抱えており
our patent was issued,
特許も取りました
I have a wonderful partner
立ち上げから共に働いた
who's been with me right from the beginning,
素晴らしいパートナーにも 恵まれています
and we've won more than 20 awards for the work that we've done.
従事した仕事で 20以上の賞を 受賞しました
But best of all,
しかし とりわけ
we've made a small dent --
小さな影響を残したこと―
a very small dent --
世界のプラスティク汚染の危機に
in the worldwide plastic pollution crisis.
ささやかながら 影響を残せたのです
(Applause)
（拍手）
And I am doing the most rewarding and meaningful work of my life right now.
私は今 やり甲斐や生きがいを 感じる仕事をしています
I can tell you there's lots of resources available to entrepreneurs of all ages,
全ての年齢の起業家に 利用可能で豊富な リソースがあると お伝えできるのですが
but what I really yearned for five years ago
私が５年前に切望したのは
was to find other first-time entrepreneurs
同年代で 初めて起業する人たちを
who were my age.
探すことでした
I wanted to connect with them.
彼らと繋がっていたかったのです
I had no role models, absolutely none.
私にはお手本になる人が １人もいなかったのです
That 20-something app developer from Silicon Valley
20歳そこそこのシリコンバレーの アプリ開発者は
was not my role model.
私のお手本ではありませんでした
(Laughter)
（笑）
I'm sure he was very clever --
頭は良いのでしょうが―
I want to do something about that,
私はそれをどうにかしたいし
and I want all of us to do something about that.
皆さんにもどうにかして欲しいのです
I want us to start talking more
高齢になって初めて
about people who don't become entrepreneurs until they are seniors.
起業する人たちのことを もっと話してもらいたいのです
Talking about these bold men and women who are checking in
基本的に周りが 仕事を辞めていく時
when their peers, in essence, are checking out.
敢えて仕事を始める 人たちことを話すのです
And then connecting all these people across industries, across regions,
業界、地域、国境を越えて そういうすべての人々と
across countries --
繋がることで
building a community.
コミュニティを作ります
You know, the Small Business Administration tells us
中小企業局によると
that 64 percent of new jobs created in the private sector in the USA
米国の民間部門で生まれた 新規雇用の64%は
are thanks to small businesses like mine.
私のような中小企業なのです
And who's to say that we'll stay forever small?
でもずっと小さいままだとは 言ってません
We have an interesting culture
私たちには 面白い文化がありまして
that really expects when you reach a certain age,
ある年齢に達したら
you're going to be golfing, or playing checkers,
１日中 ゴルフやチェッカーをしたり
or babysitting the grandkids all of the time.
孫の世話をするものだと 思われているのです
And I adore my grandchildren --
もちろん 孫は可愛いですよ
(Laughter)
（笑）
and I'm also passionate
私は 同様にグローバル市場で
about doing something meaningful in the global marketplace.
意義有ることをするのも 好きなのです
And I'm going to have lots of company.
私は会社を拡大するつもりです
The Census Bureau says that by 2050,
国政調査局によると 2050年までに
there will be 84 million seniors in this country.
米国の高齢者は 8400万人になるとのことです
That's an amazing number.
驚異的な数字ですよね
That's almost twice as many as we have today.
現在のほぼ２倍です
Can you imagine how many first-time entrepreneurs there will be
この8400万人のうち 初めて起業する人が
among 84 million people?
何人いると思いますか？
And they'll all have four decades of experience.
皆40年間の 職業経験があるのですから
(Laughter)
（笑）
So when I say, "Let's start talking more about these wonderful entrepreneurs,"
「素晴らしい起業家について もっと話そう」というのは
I mean, let's talk about their ventures,
ずっと若い世代のベンチャー企業を 取り上げるように
just as we do the ventures of their much younger counterparts.
高齢者のケースも 話しましょうという意味です
The older entrepreneurs in this country have a 70 percent success rate
米国の遅咲きの起業家は 新しい事業に取り組んで７割が
70 percent success rate.
成功率７割
We're like the Golden State Warriors of entrepreneurs --
起業界のゴールデン・ステート・ ウォーリアーのようです
(Laughter)
（笑）
(Applause)
（拍手）
And that number plummets to 28 percent for younger entrepreneurs.
若い起業家の場合の成功率は 28%にまで落ち込みます
This is according to a UK-based group called CMI.
英国が本拠の CMIによる数字です
Aren't the accomplishments of a 70-year-old entrepreneur
70歳の起業家の業績は
every bit as meaningful,
30歳の起業家の業績と同じくらい
every bit as newsworthy,
あらゆる点で意義があり
as the accomplishments of a 30-year-old entrepreneur?
あらゆる点で 報道される 価値がありませんか？
Of course they are.
当然ありますよね
That's why I'd like to make the phrase "70 over 70" just as --
だから「70人の 70歳以上の起業家」 という言葉を当たり前にして
(Laughter)
（笑）
just as commonplace as the phrase "30 under 30."
「30人の 30歳未満の起業家」と 同じようにしたいのです
(Applause)
（拍手）
Thank you.
ありがとうございました
(Cheers)
（歓声）
(Applause)
（拍手）